Hi everyone, I think we shall start in 30 seconds.
OK, so who am I?
Who I always on or not here?
So I got my bachelor's and Master's from NTQA from Athens and I recently defended my PhD basically 2
days ago.
So you should have more faith in me right now delivering the lecture.
And in terms of research interests, I'm very interested in hardware OS Co design.
Like I will deliver the virtual memory course.
This was a topic of my PhD as well tomorrow and today I also worked a lot on hardware, software Co
design.
I worked on prefetching.
That's why I'm delivering the prefetching lecture as well.
And lately I'm also working in system and architecture for physical AI and robotics.
After some internships I did, but in this lecture, we're going to talk about prefetching again.
These are the readings for this week and the last week.
I suggest reading them.
If there's one that you would spend time on, it's the last one, in my opinion, the run ahead
execution, which I will dive much deeper into today.
So let's do a very, very quick recap of what you discussed last time.
So what is prefetching?
So we want to fetch the data before it is needed by the program and this way we prefetch them,
right?
This way when the program performs the memory access, it finds the data in the caches or in the
memory in some cases.
And this is much faster compared to waiting for it on demand.
Why do we need prefetching?
Because the memory latency is high.
If you have seen what's happening right now with all the memory manufacturers, there's a dramatic
increase in the memory subsystem price where like it's 3X4 X the amount of money you would spend
five years ago.
Because people care a lot about memory latency and memory capacity.
So if we find a way to fetch data earlier and in a very accurate manner this way we can eliminate
this latency, We can hide this latency from the system.
This way whenever we access the cast, for example to retrieve our data, we will find them there and
we don't need to wait fetching them from the main memory.
And this you can generalise it across beyond caches.
You could say that I will fetch the data from my disk to the memory so that next time I access it, I
find it in the memory and not fetch it again from the disk.
So the question is, can we eliminate all different types of cache misses, for example, capacity
misses, conflict misses, coherence misses.
And this is a challenge with prefetching and prefetching specifically has one key mission.
So we want to predict which address or which addresses will be needed in the future bar application.
So when the programmer writes, I want to access X at the index I, we need to find which would be the
index that they will access next.
Will it be a stride?
Will it be a stream?
Will it be a pointer?
Chasing what?
What would they access, right.
So this works very, very well in modern systems in your processors like in Apple processors, in the
AMD, Intel processors like it works very well if you have predictable misaddress patterns.
So if the pattern that the program is using is very predictable, then we make the life of a
prefetcher much easier.
It's very, it's much easier to anticipate what will happen in the future basically and a key
property of prefetching.
And that's why if you look today in a processor, there are more than like six to seven prefetching
prefetchers all the way from the core up to the storage in the SSD is that prefetching does not
affect correctness because it's a purely opportunistic process.
We make a prediction.
OK, our data is going to be fetched from index I.
We may be wrong.
Think about it.
But who cares, right?
We fetch the data, we spent a bit more power, maybe we spend a bit more bandwidth, but it doesn't
really matter because if we do not fetch the data correctly, simply we wasted some resources.
We do not affect the correctness of the actual program.
So there is no need for any sort of state recovery, which you might have seen when we have a
misprediction, for example, misspeculation in the reorder buffer of an out of order core.
So yes, search.
For example, if we do a branch misprediction, which is very, very tricky to handle, then we would
need to roll back to the point that our program was.
And that's a much more difficult scenario to handle compared to prefetching, whether we would simply
fetch the data and that's it.
So if we want to handle more complex patterns, for example multiple regular strides, see here an
example where we have plus 1 + 2 + 3 + 1 + 2 + 3.
Even though this is not a, this is a repeating pattern.
This is, let's say a hard to predict repeating pattern and other regular accesses as you have when
you write programs, for example in C or C++ or even Python in some cases where you use linked
traversals, where you use dictionaries, when you use hash tables.
In these cases you have irregular memory accesses and these are very hard to capture with a data
prefetcher.
You show that like one of these schemes that was proposed before, it's called the path confidence
based look ahead prefetcher where we would record a series of patterns, a series of strides that
appear in the programme and what happens the next time we see the first occurrence of a stride, we
are able to predict all the next strides in the programme.
This is an approach that you can think of as a record and replay approach.
I record what happened one time in the program and I predict based on this history, I replay the
history.
In this scenario, I predicted, I recorded that 7 was followed by -6, followed by 12, followed by
6:00 and then I predicted this in the next occurrence of seven.
So one of the works you discussed was Pithia.
We worked a lot with Rahul and the whole group on that where we show that like even this is not
enough.
Taking a look at the history is one way, but learning from the history is the one of is a better
way.
Basically, if we try to understand what sort of offsets strides, what sort of aggressiveness we
should use in prefetching and make the system dynamic and self evolving, that's where we can
achieve the best of performance.
So you discussed, I guess this whole thing last time where we have a demand request.
You have some features like what is the PC that the program is currently into, which were the last
three addresses that the program was accessing.
And based on these, we use AQ learning approach.
This is a reinforcement learning approach where it's very simple.
You basically track and you try to estimate which path, which decision, which action would give you
back the largest reward in the future.
So in this example, for example, we might see that like the best thing would you assume a stride of
three and prefetch with a look ahead of two.
Which means that like I will prefetch 2 axis upfront and then I will start with a stride of two.
And this way, we would generate the prefetch inserted into some queues and make sure we are able to
update based on what happened in the future.
The moment we send the request in reinforcement learning, we cannot basically anticipate what
happened in the future, right?
So what we need to do is we need to register in the log somewhere that we've issued this prefetch.
And then when the time comes and we find out that this prefetch was very useful, we need to update
our Q table to register the fact that, OK, this action that we took under this specific state was
very beneficial for the future.
And next time we see this again, we need to follow it.
This is the performance we observed with TOPI and it's very good like across many core
configurations.
This worked very nicely.
And I will not bother you more about that.
You can see Rahul's video on the topic.
Rahul is another graduate PG student.
And this is a great book.
Like if someone wants to understand deeply reinforcement learning statistics and how you can
navigate through the space of non supervised learning, I think this is a great read.
It's sort of a very nice read.
I read it in the first year of my PhD basically.
So now let's have more fun with prefetching.
So as I discussed before, a prefetcher needs to do many things right.
It might need to capture strides, you might need to capture weird stream patterns, multiple multi
stride patterns.
And that's why.
In most modern processors we are using multiple prefetchers to cover many access patterns and this
provides one key advantage, better prefetch coverage.
So what does that mean if my program is doing both streams, strides, irregular access patterns?
If I employ 3 prefetchers, one for it's objective, then I can basically capture all of them, but at
the cost of one thing, of many things.
Basically it's more complex, right?
I need to have many designs like the processors.
Right now the, the current processors you're using has six to seven prefetchers, some of the L1
cache, some of the L2 cache.
And the problem is that they, the whole research right now is moving around coordinating this
prefetcher.
So you basically need to find a way to activate 1 prefetcher for one part of the program, deactivate
the others for some other part of the program, and somehow holistically manage this thing right.
The second is that it's more bandwidth intensive.
And what does that mean?
If I have let's say 6 prefetchers in the system and I'm very aggressive when I turn them on all on,
then I start sending lots of requests to main memory.
So if my main memory does not have enough bandwidth to supply to provide all the data, then I start
saturating potentially both the prefetched requests because they cannot arrive in time and the data
requests would get hurt because you're prefetching so much that you're creating a bot link in the
pipe between the memory and the processor.
So in real systems, when we prefetching a multi core system, we want to prefetch shared data, right?
And in many cases with prefetching shared data, we avoid coherence misses.
So what does this mean?
So whenever a process accesses the L1 cache, right in the multi core lecture you figured out that
like there is a thing called coherence where we're basically trying to find out where is our data
did some other process access our data that does it have it in the cache?
So if I prefetch shared data, this means that I already prefetch this look up where I find out what
is the coherence, the coherent state of this data.
Second, prefetching efficiency is a lot more is a lot more important in the multicore systems.
Why?
Because in a multicore system where we have multiple processes competing for memory bandwidth, then
and we might have, let's say 10 cores with six prefetchers for each core, this might mean 60
prefetchers in the system working separately doing their job.
So we need to be a lot more trying to preserve the bandwidth so that we do not destroy the
performance of other cores running in the system, right?
For example, some of you might have seen this when you launch PowerPoint and your presentation is 20
megabytes.
If you try to run another application next to it, probably it's hurting so much.
That's because PowerPoint is trying to prefetch the next slides of the presentation you're going
through.
And this kills everything in your system.
I have the problem in my MacBook as well.
It's the same thing.
So, and the other problem is this, right?
So when one course and like say that one core would benefit a lot from prefetching, right?
The other course are, OK, they're not running anything or they're running some simplistic
application.
This core that generates lots of prefetches, it's fetching data at multiple levels of the caches.
So you might find data from this core and spill over in the last level cache which is shared across
all cores.
You have the bus contention as we discussed and as you have seen in DRAM where you have discussed a
lot, you start contending for resources in the banks which row would be activated, which part of
the bus will be affected and in generally creates a whole contention in the in the system.
So in this work, which was published in HPCA 2009, we demonstrated like I, I manually demonstrated
that like if you employ A specialised method for prefetching linked data structures like
dictionaries like hash tables or closed loop hash tables, then you basically can reduce a lot this
bandwidth requirements of prefetching.
And we also did more work on that where we showed that I man, again in Micro 2009, he showed that
like if you're using hierarchical control of prefetchers, which means I'm using both a prefetcher
at it's core, a controller at it's core that either toggles on and off the prefetcher as well as a
prefetcher that covers all the prefetchers of all cores.
Then I can also get better performance.
This work in a similar speed where we demonstrate that like it's very important that you tune the
furnace in the system and coordinate it with prefetching.
And this is very relevant for memory controllers as well DM controllers because if the memory
controller receives requests from prefetching.
They need to schedule them along with data requests.
So you need to have an algorithm to anticipate what would be the benefit of prefetching this data
versus servicing the actual data.
And this is what we are addressing this work.
This is one of the nicest and simplest words that I've seen on the field where Vivek actually
proposed the following thing.
So whenever you have a prefetcher, fetch data on your last level cast.
You do not know the actual benefit of this prefetch right a priori.
So you know it only posteriori because the data request will come later.
So what you do is you have a predictor, A specialised predictor beyond the prefetcher that tells
you, OK, this prefetch is going to be useful.
So prioritise keeping it in the cast because it's going to be useful in the future.
If you see that this request is not useful and it's going to be useless and you predict that using
your tiny predictor, then you simply insert it with very low priority in the cases.
So if a demand request need to take place in the CAS for instead of this prefetched request, then it
this will happen and it will you will get bad performance without sacrificing CAS resources.
And now the very exciting topics, execution based prefetching.
Right now we talked about the prefetcher where you're basically have as an input some stream of
memory accesses, right?
And you're trying to predict the following stream of memory accesses.
What will happen in the future?
But there is another class of works called execution based professors.
And in this example is that we will in this.
The idea of this paradigm is that we will pre execute a piece of program solely for prefetching
data.
So imagine if somehow your core was able to pre execute code that leads to cache misses before the
actual main thread runs.
And this way you can pre fill the data in the caches and you find them when the main thread arrives.
This could a speculative thread approach where the pre executed programme piece can be considered a
thread and the speculative thread in some cases can be executed on a separate core.
We execute it on a separate hardware thread context, which means that like I have two sort of lanes
in my core where I can execute both the main thread and the lightweight speculative thread.
Or in some cases you could use a single context which I will show you later where you could simply
swap between threads that prefetch and threads that execute.
So this is a very big paradigm like it's called freight based pre execution.
And there, these are three Seminole works on the topic that form the basis for many other works with
hundreds of citations where basically we we can achieve 2 things when we're executing the program.
In some cases we can fork something.
Fork means that we will duplicate.
We will basically create another instance of the program using a nano thread.
This nano thread you can think of it as a very simple form of thread that runs in parallel with your
main thread and tries to anticipate and calculate the outcome of a branch.
This is not only useful for prefetching, this is useful for predicting the outcome of a branch.
So you can figure out the outcome of branch much earlier and you don't need to make a prediction.
Basically you can say, OK, this is the result of the branch, you do not need to predict.
We avoid any sort of misspeculation like we are sure that this is the correct path taken.
At the same time you can fork another thread whose only job like has nothing to do with branches.
And what it does is is it executes some piece of code that replicates your program.
And this way it generates cache misses.
It pre generates the cache misses that your programme would generate in the future.
And this way when the programme reaches this load it experiences a cache hit.
Why?
Because the nano thread on the left fetch the data, executed the code, the simplistic version of the
code much earlier, fetch the data and you have a load that hit in the caches.
And this way you get very significant speed up.
Any questions?
There are three ways of doing that.
The first way is that you block basically the the main thread spawns the nano thread and you have 33
techniques to do that, right?
One is I stop, I wait for the nano thread that runs faster to to calculate the branch.
But this is meh for performance because I need to wait right?
So the second approach is called a synchronous non blocking, which means that I spawned the thread.
It runs in a separate core and I make sure that like the two contexts registers the stack, all of it
is replicated.
So there is no way that you would need synchronization or any other sort of primitive between these
two.
Also, it's purely opportunistic, right?
The only thing you need to do in terms of prefetching is either you find the data or not.
You do not need to.
If you if you pay the penalty of synchronising, then you might miss the benefits of what you did
right?
Is that clear?
Anyone else?
Thank you.
So I'm going to talk right now about run ahead execution.
Run ahead execution was the PSD thesis of my advisor and the whole thing is falling on me to
describe.
So we have the currently order buffers as you have seen, out of order course you have windows,
right?
And these windows basically support multiple in flight instructions.
So as you can see here, there's an 8 entry instruction window.
So we have at the top the old instruction Bing a load, right?
And what did we see?
We see that this load takes 100 cycles to execute.
We have a branch next and some more instructions next.
So can someone tell me what's the problem with the rest of the instructions in this window?
Given that the old instruction is the one that is basically causing the higher latent the highest
latency, can anyone anticipate what would happen with the with the rest of instructions?
That's one thing that can happen, but the main thing that happens is that we cannot commit them,
right?
We cannot get rid of them.
We might execute them, as you correctly say, but we cannot basically commit them and retire them and
free up resources because we're waiting for this one to finish the one that would take 100 cycles.
So all of these instructions are basically have a single point of failure.
The instruction that lives at the top of the window, if this instruction is not serviced as fast as
possible, all of the other instructions will wait.
And not only that, the younger instructions that might be available to fetch might also not be
executed because we do not have space in the instruction window to add them, right?
And the whole system, the whole processor is waiting until this miss is serviced.
And which means that the whole reorder buffer, the instruction window is waiting for 100 cycles
doing nothing.
It's not commuting anything basically.
So this long latency cast misses as responsible for all these full windows stalls here.
So in this plot honour basically for your thesis demonstrated that if we're using a 128 entry
window, 128 entries in the window, most of the penalty you get from waiting comes because of long
latency misses because you're missing up the L2 cast.
If you make the window many times larger, like 2048 entry window, then you see that this percent
that gets much smaller.
Why?
Because you make your window much larger, you can fetch more instructions and you have less
dependence on the top because you can keep fetching and fetching and fetching.
And the rate at which you fetch much is the rate at which you retire basically.
So the problem is that out of order execution, as you can understand, requires this sort of very
large instruction windows.
We want to have large instruction windows to tolerate all these memory latency.
The higher the memory latency, the largest the window we would need, right?
Because then we need to match the rate at which we fetch with the rate at which we commit.
So as memory latency increases, the problem is that we would need to scale the instruction window
size.
But if we want low power and energy consumption sort, critical path execution and load design and
verification complexity, we cannot afford that because jumping from A128 entry window to a 2K entry
window, it's a very, very expensive process, both for industry and for anyone who wants to design A
processor.
So running it.
Execution proposed at HPCA 2003 is a technique where you try to combine memory parallelism benefits.
Basically you try to get the the memory.
Level parallelism benefits assuming you have a very large instruction window.
It's as if you have a very large instruction window but without having it.
So when the old on the oldest instruction as I showed you before is a long latency cache miss, what
do we do?
We checkpoint the architectural state and enter the run ahead mode.
So which means we stop, right?
And we enter run ahead mode and then in run ahead mode we speculatively pre pre execute instructions
of the program while we're waiting for the main memory access to finish.
And this way when we pre execute, our only goal is to fetch the next data required by the processor
so that we issue pre fetches and we avoid future Cos misses.
This way we have long latency instruction to to achieve this we have long latency instructions like
divisions for example being marked as invalid and we drop them and we pray that they will not
affect us from prefetching right.
This way we can basically execute a lot more prefetches in the window that we have left, which whose
duration is usually the main memory access latency.
So when the original mystery turns where we're we're waiting, we we restore the checkpoint to the
execution state that we were, to the architectural state that we were.
We flash the pipeline with all these prefets, bug prefetch instructions and we resume the normal
execution.
This is an example of run here.
So you can see here a scenario where we have a very large run reorder buffer, many windows, many
number of entries in the window, and we have a perfect cache, which means that we hit always,
right?
So we compute the instruction, we hit, then we compute the next instruction, we hit again.
That's the perfect scenario, right?
What happens when we have a small window, we compute something, we have a miss from load one and we
need to wait.
Now we need to wait for this amount of time.
So next time we compute again for the next instruction of the head of the ROB or lower, we have a
miss at the load 2 and we need to wait again because there is no other way.
We need to wait to fetch it because it blocks the ROB right in run ahead.
What we do is the following.
When load one happens, we do not simply stall.
We try to leverage the existing resources of the core to enter in a special mode.
When we run ahead, we execute instructions opportunistically in order to fetch load two.
We start and generate here the miss for load 2A lot earlier compared to the small window case.
This way we have a load one hit, which was the case before as well because we waited for this amount
of time.
But after we compute this instruction, we have a load two hit because the load 2 was issued much
earlier compared to the small window without run ahead, right?
So what do you understand from this?
But if even if we use a small window, if we're able to leverage it and overlap the miss latency, the
stall with actual print computation, the run ahead mode, then we can basically hide many cycles
from the pipeline.
So what are the benefits of run ahead?
The pressure speculatively prefetches pre executes the program far ahead into the instruction stream
without stalling for long latency instructions.
And the very important one here is that pre executed loads and stores which are independent of the
L2 miss instructions, which means that like they do not depend on the ROB on the top of the ROB
instruction, they're very accurate because why are they very accurate?
Because you're executing the actual program.
So if you're executing the actual program this way, you make sure that the that data addresses
you're generating are correct and instructions in the predicted on the predicted program path are
prefetched into the instruction cast and other cast levels.
This is another benefit.
If I start executing instructions which are in the future then I will also prefer the instructions
of the programme, not just the date of the programme.
One more benefit is that if if we have more of these structures in the system that are history
based.
If I go into the future and start executing in futuristic instructions then I will basically pre
train them.
I will pre train both my hardware prefetcher that lives in the L2 cars and I will also pre train my
branch predictor tables and this way I can basically convert much faster to a system that has high
accuracy.
I wanted to show you an example.
Does anyone have any question on how run ahead works?
OK, I know.
Oh, Sir, Yes, Sir.
So I wanted to ask if during your own 100 execution you have another cache.
So yeah.
So in this scenario, right, So in run ahead, you're stopping when you have the load one miss, you're
stopping, right, because you the instructions at the top of the ROB and you stop.
So you remove all the instructions you had, you fetch the next one that would that should be
executed and you have another load miss.
So as you correctly say, what do we do?
So the whole point of run ahead is instead of waiting for this second load, you simply issue a
prefetch for it.
You just execute it.
You you you try to fetch the data in the cache hierarchy so that when the programme resumes from the
correct point, when it restores and continues with the correct instruction again, you would
basically fetch you would have already fetched in the cache hierarchy.
That's the whole point that you're basically waiting for the load one, the load 1 stall and at the
same time you're pre fetching the load 2.
So next when you restore from the load one miss stall time, you see that the load 2 is already
fetching the cache.
That's the effect of run ahead.
You do not need to use this load.
Potentially you might not need it to not to use it to execute the run ahead programme, but the whole
purpose of the run ahead programme is to simply fetch the data of load 2 so that next time you see
load 2, it's already brought in the caches.
No.
But when you fetch, you don't lose.
Yes, you're fetching in the background.
Yes, that's the you prefetched them, right?
So you do not need, it's not a blocking load, you do not need to block on this load.
You just issue it and you forget about it and you move on, executing the rest of the instructions.
Yes, I wanted to show a more, let's say illustrative example of how run ahead works.
So let's see the following scenario.
I have three different systems which I will show you.
And these systems comes from real life.
So the processor.
So let's say that this is restaurant one, right?
And in restaurant 1, there is one person working at the kitchen, only one, right?
And this person receives orders.
Order one, order two, order three, right?
And let's agree that the long latency instructions and orders are the soups because the soup takes a
lot of time to boil.
So let's say that here you have a soup.
So imagine what would happen if one chef sits on top of the soup waiting while not executing the
other orders.
So basically if every order was a soup, they would wait for two hours then they would do the other
one.
Everybody would not be happy as you can understand right?
So this is the bud system.
If one chef just waits until the soup is boiled, then we have a problem.
So the second system.
So can someone tell me how to improve this very easily?
Like what would what would happen if I had three serfs?
I would basically have three people, three orders.
And that's very easy again, right?
3 soups, 3 orders, everybody's looking at their own soup.
That's very easy.
The problem here is that like with an average Swiss salary, I'm broke.
Like if I have 3 serfs looting at one soup, right?
So the best way of dealing with that is basically I have one SEF that is very skilled.
And what they do is that they put the soup to boil, they handle this, it's boiling, and then they
have these two orders which they can see right, and they start the preparation for these while the
soup is boiling.
This way, the chef at the last table, the last restaurant.
Is as efficient is using the same resources of the safe in the first one, but it's gaining a lot of
time and servicing the customers in a much better way compared to the one in the first one.
How does it go down?
OK, sorry.
OK, Yeah, sorry.
Right?
It's very accurate for both for prefetches, for data and for instructions.
So it's because it follows the programme path, right?
As I said, the last chef knows the orders, so he won't make a mistake.
He won't fetch a random order just because he thought some customer would order something different.
So it's very simple to implement.
Why?
Because you're basically re executing code in the same piece of hardware that you would execute your
normal program.
And there is no way, no waste of hardware context.
Which means that again, you're using this main thread that you're using for computation, you're
using it to generate the prefetches.
Also, there is no need to have a separate special purpose component to pre execute.
You can use again the same core, right?
What are some disadvantages?
First, you're executing more instructions per second, right?
As the chef, you're doing more work per second, which means you're basically consuming more power.
Also, you have you're limited by the branch prediction accuracy, which means that like if run ahead
falls into a branch during run ahead mode, then it might start making decisions based on the
predictor which are irrelevant to what the programme will do.
This way you might prefer trash in many cases.
Third, you cannot prefer dependent cache misses.
This goes back to the question of like if I do not, if I wait for the L2 cache miss, then I break
the purpose of run ahead, right?
Because I do not generate the prefetch, I wait again.
So, but if I have a data dependent miss where one load depends on another one, that's a problem
which Honour tried to solve in his dissertation.
Also, we are limited by the effectiveness of the memory level parallelism.
What does this mean?
If my processor cannot service multiple preferred requests in parallel then we will have another
sort of bottleneck because we will create resource contention and last the prefetch distance which
means how far ahead of the main thread am I going to execute is basically limited at the current
state of the thread.
Like if I'm at instruction AI cannot go and fetch the I cannot fetch instructions and pre execute
from a very different point of execution.
I need to go to instruction A + 1.
Basically the all these benefits and simplicity and all the things I discussed were basically shown
at the Sunrock, IBM Power 6 and NVIDIA Denver who all implemented one or in another way the run
ahead execution, what is the performance?
This is a very important result we show here that if we employ run ahead execution, it's 22% better
than a no professor, no run ahead scheme.
And the most important thing is that like.
You can combine it together with the prefetcher.
Basically you combine run ahead with the prefetcher in your system.
We can get even better results compared to only doing run ahead.
But this is I think the most interesting one.
This result shows that a 128 entry window, the blue, the the sorry, the red bar, the 128 entry
window with run ahead, which means they have a very lean core.
With 128 entries in the reorder buffer can almost match the performance of a 512 entry window
because we're leveraging the parallelism that we can basically extract from while waiting for
instructions for load missions to complete.
These are other nice results where like my owner showed the benefits of run ahead in both in order
and out of order course, and naturally the overheads.
When you use an in order core, which cannot at all tolerate memory access latency because every
instruction is essentially at the head of the ROB, you basically get even higher performance, and
this was shown by.
Under Chowdhury in during August 20,000 and eight in a technical report where they demonstrate the
following.
As you can see in this red line, they implement A technique called Scout and they implemented this
in the Sun computer in the Sun processor.
And they demonstrate that if you use Scout, which is a version of run Ahead, basically their version
of run Ahead, something very close, you can almost get the same performance with a four MB L2 cache
as if you have a 12 MB L2 cache.
Which means that with prefetching, prefetching VR Anna head can basically give you a discount 20
megabytes of extra overhead of extra hardware.
Yes, this is the work.
I don't know.
Published and received a tremendous amount of awards and stuff.
The biggest one, I guess the test of the time I work given to 202115 years after the paper was
published and I think many works after that.
Even after that received best paper awards coming from other groups.
Like other groups that worked in the topic, they also still push the boundary of this specific
technique in different ways.
This is 1 work.
Again, this is the Sun computer where one of the architects wrote the paper about how they
implemented runahead in the Sun computer.
And this is again follow up.
Runahead was also implemented in the IBM Power Six or one version of runahead was implemented in the
IBM Power 6.
And they, they demonstrate that like if they used to gather conventional prefetchers and runahead,
they can add additional 6% to the performance, right?
So whenever they combine these two, they get even high performance.
And it was also implemented in the 64 bit ARM processor of NVIDIA, it's called Denver.
This is a nice article that summarizes all the the whole architecture and they show how how this
works here and the performance they get lots of performance benefits with that.
And Honor in his dissertation proposed many, let's say follow-ups on how to deal with different
things, the techniques for efficient processing and run ahead execution engines.
This was basically one of the techniques where he tried to reduce the power because executing extra
instructions leads to power increase, right?
I execute more stuff in the same amount of time, which means I I increase power and honor is trying
to show how you can employ techniques to reduce the power requirements.
In the 2nd paper.
The other's value delta prediction is showing how you can basically enable some hints so that you
can prefetch for content, do some sort of content directed prefetching.
Which means if I even if I have a data dependency during run ahead, I can resolve it in a with a
trick basically.
And also owners show that like in many cases, even if run ahead sometimes goes into the wrong path
of of speculation.
Let's say you see a branch you miss, you misspeculate during granahead in this work shows that even
in this scenario you might fetch data in the mispeculation path that might be useful for the
correct execution path in the future.
And this is a very counter intuitive thing, right?
Like I fetch data from the wrong execution path of the code and then I benefit in the correct
execution path of the code.
So energy inefficiency is one thing that he tried to deal with.
Then effectiveness for pointer intensive applications against this work and the resolvable branch
mispredictions in run ahead mode where he showed what I discussed.
Like if you cannot recover from an L2 misdata dependent branch, you still might have benefits from
run ahead.
Again, these were the works of his thesis.
This was in the IEEE microtopics.
This is the work where he predicted the linked list and the pointer chasing.
And how did this work in this paper?
That's very cute actually.
So you have a load L1 miss, and again, you need to go into the run ahead window, right?
You need to go into the run ahead mode.
When you see that you cannot compute an address, you basically mark it as invalid.
Normally it's like I do not know the registers because I they depend on load one.
I cannot prefetch anything because I do not know what the instructions should fetch, right?
So next time you have a load miss again, you're failing because we didn't prefetch anything for
load.
So what Arnold did here is that at the load one miss, he found a way to value predict, which means
that OK, I'm missing load one, but I will now predict the value that probably I will fetch for load
one.
And he showed that if this value is a pointer, for example, it's very easy to predict that.
So this way when load 2 comes, you can compute the address of load 2 which depends on the value that
you predicted.
So you make all these nested predictions and this way you fetch load two, you prefetch load 2, so
next time you execute the load two, you basically hit and this way you save important cycles which
were not saved before in the classic run ahead.
This is the work and looking in the past at the time there were many works that like were focusing
on increasing the reorder buffer size and designing bigger and more complicated machines and run.
I had basically is a very, let's say simple and efficient and intuitive way of dealing with the
problem.
It generated basically a different way of thinking of like let's keep the course small and try to
get the heck out of it.
Basically you try to.
Levered you that's not this possible, you use automat expect.
Execution only for prefetching.
You don't do it for anything else.
You don't pre compute, pre compute for any other reason.
And also you can have synergies with prefetching and branch prediction.
And they're like many, many lines of work that started from this one important precedent.
There was one paper in 1997 which was proposing something very similar to this, but for in order
processors.
This is from James Dundas and Trevor Muddz and inspiration comes from this called Whitey's like wild
and crazy ideas workshop, I think from 1998, where they show they like they provided some, let's
say very high level instructions on how how someone could do run ahead and looking to the future.
Micro architecture is very important, especially memory.
Run Ahead is a great example of harmonious industry, academia, academia collaboration honoured I
think explore Run ahead during his all of his internships in the first years of his PhD.
And it's a very fundamental problem, the problem of prefetching you will meet it in LLMS and
whatever you can imagine basically right.
And it is well fundamental solutions, the solutions that you see here about Run Ahead and the
processor, they can be used potentially for many other subsystems and many other subtopics of
computing.
Yes, as I said, like around I had received a citation for the test time test of the time award.
And I think this is the third one is the most important thing.
It's spawned a new area of research basically that people have worked a lot on and there are many
groups that even still work on it.
I will talk about this later.
So you can take a 10 minute break and then we can discuss again going into virtual memory and some
like pep talk.
Ok, Let's continue so on.
Here has some like nice advice for you like following your passion do not get delayed by naysayers.
I guess this applies probably this your block courses, right?
So this applies to this sort of spirit.
And I agree with him on that being resilient, yes, you might fail one course that doesn't mean much.
You can take it again.
And this is during research as well, where we probably receive a lot more rejects than accepts.
In general in your research career, in your career in general, the bad moments are going to be more
than the good moments.
Yeah.
But again, this is true for your courses also in general.
Like if you focus on the through learning part, regardless of exams and all these things, things
will go well at the end of the day.
This is true also in research and learning, like yeah, the quality of how you study, for example,
can define your grades, your impact, anything that you work on, right.
And yes, you can make a good impact.
Let's see.
I'm not sure about that.
So there is a lot more on running head execution from Carnegie Mellon University, the lectures when
honour was there from the Computer architecture course, it's all on YouTube and there is a lot more
recommending material on prefetching, but owner has already given it's all online.
And now I will stop with the prefetching lecture and I will switch to the virtual memory lecture.
This is very nice blueprint that owner has written.
It's called Intelligent Architectures for Intelligent Computing Systems, where he does a very nice,
like, let's say, summary of research on how to design intelligence systems, which should be data
centric, data-driven and data aware.
So right now we're in an era where like everything is dominated by data and the decisions would take
at the core level, the decisions would take at the memory level.
And all of this is driven by the data that basically are accessed by the applications.
So virtual memory is one of the cornerstones of data.
Basically it's one of the cornerstones of modern computing systems.
And there are many nice reads here.
I would suggest the memory systems book, the handbook from 2014.
And I think we in our work in ASPLOS 2025 would do a nice background where someone can basically
learn the basics and fundamentals of virtual memory.
So what is a virtual memory?
So when you write the program, let's say you write your C, your Python, C++ program, right?
You basically do 2 things.
You write store instructions.
I store something in memory and load instructions.
So this is how you view memories.
Load, store, load, store, right?
So the ideal memory that you have in your mind while writing, writing this program is that it has
zero access time.
You don't care about its latency.
It has infinite capacity.
You do not write the program assuming you're constrained by memory capacity, right?
Has 0 cost and infinite bandwidth.
So the programmer sees virtual memory, though the programmer does not see physical memory.
This way the programmer can assume that the memory is infinite.
In reality though, the physical memory size is much smaller compared to what the programmer assumes.
So the system somehow, in a magic way, system software and hardware together, they map virtual
addresses to physical memory.
So the system automatically manages the physical memory transparently to the programmer.
And the programmer does not even know anything about the physical size of memory nor manage it.
And this way, if small physical memory we have in the system might appear very large when it comes
to the programmer.
I want to show another example, not with restaurants, but.
So imagine you write your program right?
Let's say your program is this.
You do something very simple in C or C++.
You can map this to Python.
You do this.
So what this does, you're saying I want to use an array which has 10 integers, right?
And the name that you're using when you write the program, let's say you want to do this.
So let's say that you were not, we were not using virtual memory and there is a physical memory in
the system.
Let's say that this is a physical memory, right?
And we need to store this X0 somewhere, so in.
Very but szenario the programer what say ok.
I will go to the physical location #1 because that's what I chose and I would store X of 0.
OK, so can someone tell me what would happen if another programmer who runs another program in the
system does this and this programmer decides that I need to also choose the physical location of my
data and I accidentally I want to use this location then can someone tell me what's the problem
with that?
I mean the first programmer now doesn't access the data that it probably is assumed that it would
still be there exactly.
So this programmer was writing one and let's say this programmer overwrote with 10.
So what is the problem here?
The problem is that the in this system the programmers were not given something which we call a
namespace.
So X here and X here are not in.
This should not be in the same namespace.
So we should name this something.
We should name this something.
They might be the same, but they should not map to the same thing in physical memory.
So basically, even though we gave them, the programmer gives them the same names.
They are X0 and X0.
They should not map.
We should design a system so that these two variables are not mapped to the same spot in the
physical memory.
And without virtual memory, we cannot guarantee this.
Like there is no way that we can force everybody to manage the physical memory in their own way.
This is a very hard person to do.
So we need to create something like an intermediate space where we have a dictionary essentially and
we will say, so virtual memory is a dictionary at the end of the day.
So virtual memory would do the following.
It's very simple.
It would say programmer 1 is using X0 and he will not choose the physical location that the data
will be stored to.
The system will choose it a system that is global and can basically coordinate between between these
two and says OK I will store it in position 1.
Then when programmer 2 also wants to use X 0 / y zero or anything, there is no way that here the the
system will not give one because 1 is already taken.
You cannot basically force in any way.
The programmer 2 cannot force the system to give it location one it's already taken.
There is no way that you can override the data and this is one of the main things that virtual
memory is used for.
Any questions before we continue?
So what's the problem with what I described in the board?
The system becomes more complex because I need a runtime or some sort of mechanism that magically
sees all the virtual addresses and somehow manages them and places them in the physical memory,
right?
And this is a classic example of should they offload everything to the programmers and make sure
that they place data in the correct physical spot, or should I design A runtime or a hardware
component that manages this sort of isolation?
So this is one of the reasons we need virtual memory and the benefits of the following The
programmer does not deal with physical addresses as as we discussed, each process has its own and
it has a very large virtual address space.
So it's it's programme has an independent mapping of virtual to physical addresses.
And that's very good because your Pro 2 programmes 2 same programmes might use the same virtual
addresses, but they map to different physical addresses and the runtime guarantees that.
This way we enable code and data to be located anywhere in physical memory.
You might see one visual location, but your data can live anywhere.
You can place the main anywhere you want.
And this way we can relocate and flexibly locate data.
And 2nd and the most important one is the isolation and separation of code and data of different
processes.
Also we can have data sharing.
How can we have data sharing?
If somehow the system can make sure that 22 virtual addresses point to the same data, then we can
treat this piece of data shared between two processes and we can do it for 10 processes, 100
processes.
And the benefit of this is that I basically the duplicate memory.
If you open up the same PowerPoint presentation again 10 times, it doesn't mean that like your
memory is going to explode by 10X.
Every process is going to basically point to the same physical data as the presentation.
So this is an example with a system that only uses physical memory.
And this was through in most early supercomputers and early PCs and many other embedded systems.
In this way, you have this system, you have ACPU that uses directly the physical addresses.
It's not using any sort of virtual addresses.
So the problem though is that the physical memory is of limited size.
So what happens if you need more?
So for example, if you have a disk, should the programmer make sure that some data is in the disk
and some other data is in the physical memory?
Should it try to like manipulate the movement, orchestrate the movement between devices?
And what happens if multiple programs may need the physical memory as we discussed?
Like in this scenario the programmer would need to make sure that different programs do not touch
the same physical locations if you were using only physical memory.
Also, the ISA, as you discussed before, for example, might have 64 bits for its memory address,
right?
So it has a other space that's much larger compared to the physical memory space.
You might have a 64 bit other space with by addressability.
What if you don't have enough physical memory?
Like what happens if you choose a virtual address that's going beyond the scope of the physical
memory, right?
So these are the difficulties of direct physical addressing.
Like the programmer needs to manage the physical memory space, which is very inconvenient and
difficult.
It's difficult to support code and data relocation.
So the addresses are directly specified in the program.
And it's difficult to also support multiple processes because of the concurrency.
Like we would need another sort of mechanism that guarantees isolation, which is very hard to
design.
And it would be also difficult to support data and code sharing across processes.
So one important thing is that like if you would need to share data between two processes, then the
two processes would need to agree before running that this is the location in the physical memory
that we will place the common data, right?
So how does virtual memory work?
So we give each programme the illusion of a very large address space, the virtual address space,
even if we have a very small physical memory.
And this way the programmer does not worry about managing their physical memory within a process or
across processes.
And they assume that they have an infinite amount of physical memory.
And the hardware and the software, specifically the operating system and the hardware cooperatively
automatically manage the physical memory space to provide the illusion that everything is
maintained by independent process.
And the basic mechanism is in direction and mapping of addresses.
So when you write your program and you're accessing let's say again X of 0, right, you're generating
and you do a printf or a print and you try to see the address of this X0, that is a virtual
address.
You cannot see the physical address without probably some escalated privileges in the system, right?
So it is not the physical address, the one you're seeing which we send to the physical memory.
This is called linear address in X86 and the system, the processor, as I will describe probably
tomorrow, has a mechanism that maps this virtual address to a physical one while the program is
running.
So even though the programmer writes requests and programs with visual addresses, these
automatically at the hardware level get translated into physical addresses.
This is called the real address in X86.
So other translation is a mechanism that can be implemented in the hardware and software together.
And you can see here 2 applications, right?
You can see two applications.
They have two different visual address spaces and this is your physical memory that represents the
physical address space.
So the first thing we do is this is a convention, we split the whole space in something called
pages.
These are fixed chunks, usually in most systems 4 kilobytes, where and the mapping we established is
between.
Four KB virtual pages to four KB physical pages.
However, this requires an indirection because then we need to map 1 virtual page number to a
physical page number.
And this indirection is provided by a virtual to physical address mapping, which you can very easily
think as a dictionary.
I go with my virtual page number.
I retrieve back my physical page number.
There are four key issues with this sort of indirection mapping.
First is when do we map?
Like when do I make a decision of mapping a virtual address to a physical address?
Most modern systems, what they do is the following.
Whenever you write your program and you do a write, you write.
You initialize an array with zeros, for example.
It immediately creates all the virtual to physical mappings.
It puts the zeros in memory.
What is the mapping granularity?
As I said, most modern systems use 4 kilobytes.
The chunk size that we split memory into is 4 kilobytes.
There are also more systems, for example Apple right now is not using 4 kilobytes, using 16
kilobytes and maybe transitions to a new page size in the future.
Then where and how do we store the virtual to physical mappings?
So there is a dictionary as we discussed, right, that contains the translations.
The question is, how do we store this?
Do we store it at the software level?
Do we keep hardware structures for it?
And last, what do we do when the other space is full?
So let's say that all of the physical sports are used, right?
We need to decide somehow, whenever we want to map something new, what to evict from the main memory
which we will place potential in the disk or we will place somewhere else.
So this is the abstractions, it's the visual other space is divided into pages and the physical
other space is divided into frames.
Essentially there is no difference between frames and pages as an abstraction.
We just use different names because it's weird saying virtual pages, physical pages and the virtual
page is mapped to a physical frame if the page is in physical memory and the location of the disk
otherwise.
So even access visual page is not in memory but on the disk.
We need to do the following.
We need to fetch the data from the disk inside the memory and establish a mapping from the visual
page to the location that we fetch the data in from the disk and the data structure.
The dictionary that stores the mappings, the visual, the physical mappings is the page table.
So you can think of physical memory as a cast.
And in other words, like physical memory is a cast of pages which we store in the disk.
So you can think of it as a fully associative cast in modern systems because a virtual page can
reside in any location in the in any physical frame, in any location in physical memory.
And there are similar casting issues that exist that we have covered in earlier lectures, like where
and how to find a page in the cast, when to remove, what to remove from the cache.
Like should we use large small pages?
Like do we use different page sizes?
And what's a write policy?
For example, if I write something in my memory and then I need to evict it in the disk, do I do it
in a write back manner or in a write through manner?
This is the analogies that you can see here.
And this is an example of what can happen actually in a real system.
You can see visual addresses coming here from the programme, right?
And some of these pages, as you can see, especially the white ones, are basically mapped to your
physical memory.
This means that you can translate them normally with a page table right while the program is
running, while some of them are stored in the hard disk.
So if the program is running and you do not find something in the page table, this means that data
is in your disk.
So you need to stop the program execution, you need to let the OS take over, bring your data from
the hard drive, place it in the memory, create the mapping, and then your page table is updated
with the correct address and the translation.
This is an example that created where you have a virtual memory size which is let's say 2 gigabytes
and a physical memory size at 128 megabytes.
And this is the total size of memory is 2 to the power of 27 bytes, right?
So the page size is 4 kilobytes with the power of 12.
And this is the organization.
We have 31 bits for the virtual address.
You can see here is because it's two to the 31 bytes 27 bits for the physical address because we
have to do the 27 bytes physical memory.
And the page offset is 12 bits.
So the number of virtual pages we have in the system is 2 to the power of 31 / 2 to the power of 12,
which means we have 19 bits for the virtual page number and we have 15 bits for the physical page
number.
And this is how we translate.
So we need to translate only the top bits of the virtual page of the virtual address to the physical
page number.
Can someone tell me why we don't need to translate the offset?
Like if we use a four KB page, why don't I need to translate the last 12 bits?
Because the pages are a nine so that the offset is always the same, correct?
Yes, which means that the offset does not change when I have a four KB chunk.
I do not need to translate internally in the four KB chunk, the address will not change, right?
I simply need to use the same offset.
What I need to translate is the upper bits is the location of the 19 bits to this 15 bits in the
physical memory.
So that's what I'm responsible for translating.
So can you tell me, can someone tell me what happens if the page offset becomes very large?
Like what is the effect here?
Like if a page offset becomes 25 bits, that's true.
We restrict, that's true because I mean, the chunk becomes larger, right?
But what is the benefit?
We get more pages or no?
But if you increase the page offset, you don't get more pages, right?
If you increase the page offset from let's say 4 kilobytes to 2 megabytes or one GB, then yes, the
dictionary becomes smaller because you need to map 1 GB virtual pages to 1 GB physical pages, and
there are only a few 1 GB physical pages in the system.
So this immediately makes your dictionary a lot smaller.
So the page table is essentially a structure that has an entry for each virtual page and it has a
validity bit.
The validity bit tells us whether the virtual page is located in physical memory or not.
If it's not valid, it means that probably it's located in the disk.
There are more complicated scenarios which I won't discuss now.
And the second and most important thing, it has the physical page number.
The physical page number is where the virtual page is located in the physical memory.
Also it has some more information, some metadata like it was this page frequently used?
Is this page dirty or modified?
Do I have permissions to access it?
And this is what you can see for example as a page table where you have some specific pages being
allocated and their physical page numbers.
Let's see this example.
So in this example, we want to do the following.
We want to take this address that we had before as well, the zero X0002 with a page offset of
75-C7047C.
And then we want to translate it, right?
So we want to translate only the visual page number, the offset, we leave it as is.
And if there's any question in your exam, don't translate the offset, OK, because many of you do
that in the exams.
Just note this down do not translate the offset.
OK, so you take the virtual page number and then you want to map it to the physical memory by taking
a look at what the page table says.
So the virtual page number is 2.
So what I do is very simple.
I go to the third entry in the page table 012, so it's 012, and I see that the page table tells me,
oh, that's nice.
The page, the page is valid, the virtual page is valid, and the physical page number is 0X7 FFF.
So when I want to form right now, the physical address, I take the physical page number which is 0X7
FFF and I concatenate it with a page offset, which doesn't change, right?
These are the 12 last bits.
So my final physical address after accessing the page table is 0X7 FFF 47 C Any questions here?
OK, so one question is how does the hardware know where to start looking at?
Because this is a an array of contiguous elements right?
So hardware in order to be able to take a look at the second entry of the page table, it has a.
Specific register which we call the page stable base register.
The page stable base register gives us directly a pointer to the first entry.
This way we can form the index to the second element of the page table in this scenario and we can
access the correct piece of data, retrieve the 0X7 FFF the physical page number and form the
physical address.
OK, so the next one is like what is the physical address of virtual address 0X5F20?
So the first thing we would need to do in this scenario again is to find the page table entry that
contains the translation for the corresponding virtual page number.
And we want to then look up the physical page number and form this way the physical address like
this is the actual data physical address that we're fetching the page table from.
It's the page table register, the base register which points here.
This is index 0 plus the VPN which acts as a key.
Like if I want to access the first VPN, I will go to 0 because this will be 0.
If I want to access VPN equals 1 then I would go to PT size which is 8 bytes which means I would add
PTPTB R + 8 which points to the second entry right?
Is it clear for everyone this one?
OK and then how do we how do I search again?
This is a more difficult scenario.
Let's say I have VPN 5 and page offset F20 right?
So I have 0X0005.
I go to the 6th location here it's like 012345 which is the 6th 1 and I find out that this data is
mapped to the physical page number which is equal to 1.
So I form the physical address by concatenating the one which is the physical page number and the
page offset which is F20.
The page offset gives me the internal index into the page and the physical page number gives me the
external index into the page.
So what happens if we have this address VPN 7?
In VPN 7 we go to the for 8th to the 8th index and unfortunately we find that our data is not in
memory.
Why?
Because the validity bit is 0.
This means that the page table says.
I'm don't have a clue of where is the data, so someone needs to basically handle this specific
exception.
In modern systems, this is an exception.
Whenever your processor says OK, the paid table doesn't have the data, it immediately lands an
exception.
It stops executing the program.
The operating system takes over and tries to resolve the location of the data.
So there is a big a big a big issue with the paid table and what I described.
Let's say that we have a 64 bit virtual address and a 40 bit physical address.
So the question is if I need to form one key for each virtual page number, how large would the page
table be if I allocated like a very large array?
Can someone tell me almost it's to the power of 52 because yes.
So can we allocate such an array in our memories?
I don't think so.
This is at the order of like beta, right?
So.
And that would be just for one process.
So imagine if for one process I allocate to the power of 54 bytes.
So the basic reason why we don't need to allocate this amount, this large amount of of an array is
that probably my program will not use the whole physical address space, right?
And the whole design of the page table in modern processors is shaped around this assumption that my
virtual, the, the program that I'm running is not using even the 50 or the 20% of the whole virtual
address space that's available, all the 40 bits, let's say, or all the 64 bits.
So the challenge one then is that the page table is large.
So we need to make sure that though that some part of it is at least located in the physical memory.
And one solution to that is multi level hierarchical page tables.
So how does this work?
We want to organize the page table in hierarchical.
Manner.
And we want to do that so that only some parts of the page table are allocated in physical memory.
So how does this work?
I will try to give you the intuitive idea.
First.
If there are big chunks of your of your page table which are not used, we want to simply encode them
with a zero.
We want to simply encode them with a zero and say OK, I will have a zero there and I do not need
this will point nowhere.
Basically this will mean that the data at the last level is empty.
I do not need to map anything to it.
This is essentially what this structure does.
So the first level of the page table will have a small first level.
It has a small number of entries, let's say 50.
Is is needs to be in physical memory.
So we only need to store this and then needed second level page table will be kept in physical
memory only if it stores some physical addresses, the information about some physical addresses.
So this is an example, right?
So you can see here that I'm splitting right now my virtual address into more chunks.
And I'm saying, OK, I will try to map first these 9 bits to the page table.
I take them, it's like 0, which means that if these 9 bits are 0, this means that from this 512
entries, this is valid, right?
This means that from my whole virtual address space, right, only two, two chunks are mapped to
physical memory, the first one and the last one.
This means that the first one, the the second one and the last one, the first one, all the
intermediate ones and this one do not need to be allocated.
We do not need to create a page table for them because they're not mapped in the physical memory.
So in this scenario, we would create the last level page table entry, another level just for the
last part and the last part.
Here this chunk would create a pointer would store a pointer to the last level of the page table.
So in this example we would need how many accesses, how many memory accesses would we need to fetch
the translation?
Like from the moment we start from the virtual address till the moment we resolve the final physical
page number?
How many memory accesses do I need to do?
How many steps do I need to follow in this example?
And then OK, so you have two accesses for the page table and one for the final data fetch right?
Because you do not need to do more than two access for the page table.
You you load first this one right?
You use this as a pointer to the final level.
You fetch the final level and basically we did 2 accesses for the page table and three for the whole
physical memory access.
Like after you form the physical address, you send the whole of it to the memory hierarchy.
I will also explain more things about the page table tomorrow because it's the hardest concept of
virtual memory, especially the multi level page table.
In modern systems they're not using 2 levels, they're using 4, which makes things even more
complicated.
So you can see here how X86 does that, where there is a 32 bit system where you have basically 2
levels.
You would basically use the top bits to access the first level of the page table and then you
recursively try to reach the leaf.
You can think of it as a tree.
This is called the prefix tree in computer science where you start forming.
Let's say you take part of the address, you access a piece of data with a larger piece of the
address.
By using the next number of bits, you access another piece of data until you find a leaf.
I can give you pointers to more about the radix.
This called the radix 3.
Basically the important thing is like as I said before, in X86 we need a base pointer.
We need to know where is the first route of the page table and that's what the role of the CR 3 is.
The CR 3 is controlled editor 3 in X86 systems.
With the operating system sets it for a process and then the hardware can basically say, OK, I will
fetch the first level of the page table from this specific register.
The first level would have already the pointers for the next level, so we do not need to store extra
registers because they would already be fetched by the next levels.
So the page table in the next 8664, in most of your systems right now, it's organise in this way.
It has four levels.
You need to split your address into four different parts and then you recursively access four
different frames, four different blocks of page table.
You access the first level, you find the pointer to the next level, you concatenate it with the 9
bits, you go and find the pointer from the next level, and only from the last level you're able to
retrieve the physical page number.
So all these requires 4 memory accesses.
So in a in a system you need to access 4 levels of the dictionary to be able to retrieve the page
table, the physical page number.
So we discussed a lot about challenge number one.
So the second challenge is that right now, as we discussed, the page table needs to do more memory
access, right?
So for each memory access you're doing, you need to be able to fetch more data than simply the
actual data fetch you're doing.
You need to fetch the page table.
And you would do, in the best case scenario, one access, 1 memory access for the other translation,
and one access to data to the physical address of the data.
So you would need 2 memory accesses at least to serving to service the instruction Fets or a load
and store and this would greatly degrade execution time.
So imagine if you have N levels of paid stable of a paid stable, then the number of accesses would
increase with a number of levels you have.
But there are many techniques which try to deal with that.
So let's see how we perform other translation of the hardware level to support visual memory.
We want both hardware and software support.
So the page table as I described before is stored in the main memory and it's the job of the
software in this scenario, the operating system to basically populate the page table, update the
dictionary and decide what to replace in physical memory.
It probably also needs to update the page table based register like the the pointer to the page
table whenever you switch the process that you're running in the core, right?
You also need to handle page faults.
Pageful is the process of not finding a mapping.
So I go to the page table, the page table says I don't have a mapping and this raises A pageful
which is an exception.
So how does the CPU discover the visual to physical mapping without this translation?
So let me see.
OK, the core right now that you have in your systems sends a virtual address to the memory hierarchy
and the memory hierarchy somehow has the page table in it.
You access the page table, you retrieve back the page table entry.
The page table entry we refer to as the last level of the page table or the final level of the page
table that stores the actual page table number, the physical page number.
But if we would do this every time, then I would need to send one request for the page for for the
page table in every memory request.
And the question is how can we speed up this process?
So you can think of the pays table again as A tag store, which is what you saw in caches, right?
It's a stag store for the physical memory data store.
It stores the mapping between virtual memory and physical memory.
And it needs the validity bit, the tag bits, support for placement, dirty bits, protection bits.
We're going to talk tomorrow about protection, which is another key aspect of virtual memory.
So now let's see who, who and how we establish the physical mapping.
So we have a, an application, right?
And we have the virtual address space.
So you're doing again, X of 0 = 1.
That's the only thing the application is doing.
And X of 0 belongs in that part of the virtual address space.
You can think of it, it's in the square part in the physical memory.
We want to ideally place our data there, right?
So the question is who places the data?
The answer is that we first the the core first raise an exception, a fault because the virtual
address is not mapped to physical memory.
So it loaded the page stable, figured out the data.
Up there and the data is finally not mapped in physical memory, so the operating system takes over
which handles the physical memory allocation.
You can think of the operating system as an entity is as another piece of software that while the
application is running, you stop the application, you fetch another piece of software which is the
operating system and is responsible for performing the allocation.
How does it do it?
It stalls the application very order buffer and everything is stopped.
You flash it, you checkpoint it, and then you start fetching A handler for the page fault.
A handler is a specific event triggered program.
A page fault happened.
I fetch the handler and the operating system.
The main thing that it does is at first searches for free physical space in memory.
If there is free space in memory, then I can allocate my data there, right?
This is the case of a minor fault.
That's the easy thing.
The hard thing is when the OS, the operating system finds out that OK, this X0 refers to some file
that is stored in a disk and it's not in memory, it's in the disk and I need to fetch it from the
disk to the memory.
And not only that, I also need to find free space in the physical memory for this piece of the file.
This is called the major page fault and this is very expensive in the system.
It might cause it might take order of milliseconds to run because it needs to issue a data fetch
from the disk and copy the data in the physical memory.
After the operating system does that, it stores or updates the visual, the new virtual to physical
address mapping in the page table, which is also stored in memory.
But the OS has direct access to physical memory and it doesn't need to go through virtual to
physical translation.
It can simply update the page table.
Any questions?
OK, so if a page is not in physical memory but in the disk, then the page table indicates that the
visual page is not in memory.
And access to the to this sort of page triggers the exception, right?
So the OS we invoke it, it moves the data from disk to memory and then other process could continue
executing normally.
But this, this process cannot execute normally because the OS has the full control over the data
placement.
So this is what would happen, right?
You would have these two virtual pages which would point to the disk in the beginning.
And after the fault is resolved, one of these pages, the second one here would now point to memory
because we have mapped it in memory.
We brought the data to memory.
It's not in the disk anymore.
This operation happens without involving the CPU.
Modern systems have something which is called ADMA Engine Direct Memory Access Engine and we need
that for the simple following reason and we will finish with that.
So why don't I want the CPU to be involved in transferring the data from the memory to the disk?
Does anyone have an idea?
I agree.
Also you would need to store them in the classes, right?
You're going to fetch them in the classes.
So yes, we want to avoid fetching data in the CPU, making the CPU run instructions for energy
reasons to just move the data between the disk and the main memory.
So we would fetch the data from the disk via the DMA engine, a specialised unit inside the main
memory, and this way we do not need to involve at all the CPU.
The CPU might be able to run another process for example in this scenario while we're waiting for
the page fault to to be performed.
And there are many ways to decide what to evict and what not from main memory when we fetch the data
from the disk, which I will discuss tomorrow.
So thanks everyone for your attention and I'll see you tomorrow.